hey everybody I'm Josh with dowse Tech
and I'm here with Jordan green hall
Jordan is a member of the Dow stack
advisory team as well as formerly
co-founder and CEO at DivX co-founder at
mp3.com and Jordan is one of the leaders
of the movement known as deep code which
contemplates among other things some of
the great challenges facing humanity and
what it will take to solve them through
the combined lens of a wide variety of
disciplines you can read some adjourn s
work on the medium publication deep code
I particularly recommend the situational
assessment series so Jordan what are you
observing in the ecosystem of humanity
that suggests a need for a project like
Dow stack and how do you see - stacks
supporting the shifts that need to occur
I think the first thing is to to kind of
caveat that there's many many different
things that are going on and lots of
them are interesting so what I'm about
to say is it necessarily the the only or
even the most interesting aspect but I
think it's one that isn't common
knowledge and I think it's a very
powerful concept that drives well you
know anybody who grasps it fully I think
will have a meaningful upgrade and their
ability to perceive what's going on and
make good choices so the the idea here
is that the the concept of rival rest's
an anti rival risks it's just call it
economics so the concept is actually
pretty simple and these days it's actual
pretty city grasps which is the the
rival risks consists of the production
and distribution of things like like a
ham sandwich or a glass of water or a
barrel of oil
meaning the kinds of things where if I
have it you don't have it and if I use
it it's gone forever
meaning that we can be rivals over its
possession and I think it's fair to say
that effectively all of economics and
all of the economy for effectively all
of civilization has been driven by the
question of how do we most effectively
Purdue
and most effectively distribute rival
rose goods and the that kind of playing
off between production and distribution
I think in many ways could just
compactly describe the tensions between
various economic theories in the past
are these political economic theories
and you know in the field of economics
there's room for concept called the non
rival risk which i think is actually a
pretty sloppy idea it's like a park or a
bus where many people can share it this
is shareable and those are interesting
but I think if you really push him to
the limit they collapse back down to the
riders it's just larger groups of people
are serrated with them but then there's
a completely different concept which is
the anti rival miss um and these are
things that those of us who spend a lot
of time in the digital sphere or in the
information sphere have intimate
familiarity with these are things like
say calculus or the English language or
well both the idea and the active
practice of the blockchain these are
these are things where not only can I
have it and then also you have II
without me losing anything but more
importantly actually it becomes more
valuable the more people who have it so
it's subject to almost inverse logics
almost inverse dynamics and as it turns
out as a consequence also completely
different economics the the kind of
economics even simple things like the
law of supply and demand just flat-out
don't apply and can't help make sense of
the anti robber is to make and so those
are those are two fundamental concepts
and then the next big piece of course is
to recognize that we are moving into an
environment where the ante to rival risk
increasingly is dominant you're moving
out of a space where scarcity and rival
hrus goods are affected everything you
have to care about and into a domain
we're designing systems that are
optimized for the generation and
and throughout his phenomenal are what
matters I mean we can tend to kind of
make it prosaic which is to say think
about the way that technology has
grasped and taking complete
responsibility for or is in the process
of taking responsibility for say food
production if we move into the zone of
vertical indoor farming and cultured
meats like imagine in ten years 85% of
all food is actually produced by those
kinds of modes that takes a fundamental
rival roars phenomena on food almost in
some sense the archetype and shows how
it has become the object and consequence
the answer is rather than the other way
around
mmm-hmm so so so the DAO as a concept in
many ways takes place in the context of
the necessity for the invention
development of a truly anti ravenous
economic system but if at a conceptual
level and at a physical level and so
while it is it's certainly the case and
I and I completely endorse notions and
thinking about and by the way even spent
a long time thinking about notions about
how the DAO revolutionizes methods of
organization and does things like
reduces transaction costs I think it's
actually more interesting more profound
more powerful to think about how the Dow
steps into the space of the anti
rivalries yep and what does that mean so
so then to kind of examine that we can
take a look at the problem of open
source and open source is I actually
maybe I'm that's the right way of
putting it it's an early stage of this
evolution it's a recognition of the fact
that there's something incredibly
powerful about the ability to create
things that are more valuable the more
share they are and therefore we should
design them to be more shared and we
should open the source and make it so
that anybody who wants to use them can
and equivalently anybody who wants to
add Gaia to them can because the
multiplicative factor is enormous but of
course what open source lacks is a
mechanism for
two distinct things one is rewarding
people you were doing that in any way
other than intrinsic which is great I
mean there could be wrong the open
source envelope has done enormous amount
of good but it in many ways reached its
limitations there are things that it has
not been able to do yeah and a part of
why it hasn't been able to do them is
because you can't make a meaningful
living in the open source world at least
no large amounts of people can't and in
particularly the most brilliant people
aren't well rewarded for contributing
their brilliance to this open comments
and this is solving this problem is one
of the things that the Dow or in this
case quite specifically Dow stack in
particular is position to do yeah and as
it turns out the other major problem
happens to be so the other side of the
same coin which is how do we go about
orienting ourselves towards the highest
kind of value that we could contribute
into this anti reverse domain if you
think about old-fashioned microeconomics
its just supply and demand which shows
up this price meaning if I have skills
at growing food and I have skills at
fixing cars and I have skills at
repairing shoes the only the easy way
for me to find out which of those I
should do is to find out which one will
pay me the most mm-hmm and that's that's
kind of the brilliance of the price
equation in a market economy yes all I
have to do is keep my eyes open through
what is paying me the most and that is
what is in fact the most valuable way
that I can contribute to the Commons but
in the and what we try to do is you try
to kind of shoehorn the anti rivalries
into that environment by inventing
intellectual property so if I can take
the output of my anti reverse Goods
ideas and I can put a fence around them
and say okay now these are now rival
risks you can kind of make them a little
bit work using supply and demand but of
course the whole point is that with
patents and trademarks and copyrights a
limit
abilities what they actually do is they
limit the global value that could be
produced and if you if you think about
the way that it's not just a one-time
meaning lots of people can benefit from
the sharing but it's also the shape of
the curve because the antivirus has this
building on the shoulders of giants
somebody invents calculus not only is it
great that everybody gets calculus but
it's also the fact that nobody else has
to ever do it again right the next
doesn't have to reinvent caucus the next
genius gets to build what's on top of
calculus and continue continue continue
so if you if you if you rate limit the
dissemination of antivirus phenomenon
not only do you - do you limit the value
of their dissemination on one level but
more importantly you actually change the
slope of the curve of what happens when
people get this ramify effective
building on the shoulders of giants
mm-hm
and so if you if you go if it's
basically run the math on that the
patent style system which is to say the
rival risk approach to an travelers
phenomena is extraordinarily in
operation and also effectively hobbles
or destroys the actual generative
capacity of those economies that operate
in that fashion and what I mean by that
is actually very important with that
what that means is that anybody or more
specifically the first group the first
economy of any meaningful size that
figures out how to actually fully orient
optimal attention to the most valuable
anti reverse contributions and then to
motivate them by fully incentivizing
them has a decisive strategic advantage
over all rival risk economies mm-hmm
okay yeah this is it's a one-way trip it
is the the metaphorical equivalent of
learning of Homo sapiens learning how to
speak versus other primates it is that
level of dissemination it is a escape
velocity shift yes it is both a hard
part as a novel problem it is a hard
problem and it is a good problem if you
solve that problem you have in many ways
one
the entirety of the of the rivals game
the game that civilization had been
playing for the past 10,000 years you
get to win that game and then you get to
play in a completely new game and
because of the velocity the shape of the
curve that happens we've begun to
resolve the antivirus questions and
again it's the question of where should
I is the potential contributor to the
ant Revis economy most fully attend
where's my genius most fully best
applied for the acceleration of the
whole um and then also how does the
whole most appropriately and effectively
reward me for doing that so that I am
fully and appropriately incentivized
that's the problem the acceleration of
that problem is what moves us into what
many people call the society of
abundance it moves us into I think
former the best statement so far is from
the book mana we talked about the
Australia project the Australia project
is exactly this or at least it's close
enough to account so we so we can come
to recapitulate we have we have the
problem that we can't actually use
supply and demand in the price equation
either to orient people's attention or
to reward their contributions in the
antivirus domain I can spend time kind
of decomposing that but in this context
the middle is just accept that as being
a and insight um and if we can figure
out how to solve that problem in
appropriate that you the imprint drivers
domain we've done something that is just
flat-out more than a good idea
it is qualitative shift in a group
capacity so this that becomes the object
that attracted me to this space and it
is also actually object that are tried
to baton to this space and and the
reason why I spent my time energy and
money supporting what my Tom was doing
was because he and the kind of people
who get what he's trying to do which is
to say the community that intrinsically
begins to gather around that project
initially in back feed and then more
concretely endow stack
are the kinds of minds with the kinds of
attitude approaches and backgrounds that
could solve this problem mm-hmm and it's
very interesting actually because when I
said that it was initially thinking was
it it might be important to think about
them whether you could solve the problem
in principle meaning you could craft a
theory about how one goes about doing
this a new model of economics or you
could solve it in practice you could
craft an architecture a technical
architecture as it turns out that
exactly the same right oddly enough and
this is actually also ends up being a
kind of a profound concept that somebody
might be moved to explore in this world
that we're operating in there is in many
ways no distinction between theory and
practice they're glued together in such
an intimate way that while one can and
should think about say the design aspect
of practice and the coding aspect of
theories so I inverted them on purpose
that's the better way of thinking about
it
meaning it's kind of like the way in the
scientific in the scientific endeavor
theory and experiment can be separated
but was only doing science when one is
doing both in a very intimate way in in
this case in this case of the antivirus
and all problems of this sort other
weathers end as many one must
simultaneously be doing writing code in
thinking and how it's actually
implemented in call it physical
architecture and doing high-level design
you have to be doing both and that's
that I think is what makes Dow stack
interesting is that they I think
intuitively get that but more
importantly have the capacity to do it
you know and this is very different than
a lot of the the native ways that one
goes about doing software development in
the in this millennium hmm
for very good reasons by the way
software development in the 21st century
has taken a very incremental and low
architecture approach speed and the
ability to simply change the things
rapidly has become a good design
methodology and in many cases that's a
good idea
but as certain cases it's completely
capable of solving the problem and I
think we have a nice simple
example which was the the transition to
aetherium at the moment of the inception
of ethereum so yes if you remember the
history of the blockchain version 1 the
Bitcoin
invention and if you think about Bitcoin
bitcoin is an example of a genius level
of focus on total system design it was
able to be instantiated in a white paper
which all at once articulated a
comprehensive system design including
all the necessary elements like really
solving the Byzantine generals problem
and also thinking about the intrinsic
motivational and scent of systems that
would drive behaviors around miners and
around consensus kind of all had to be
done at once if you didn't get it all at
once you weren't going to be able to
discover it through local
experimentation but once you did the
design work you then began the hard
problem of implementation and then now
we're in the middle of the lift vital
experiment where we discover all kinds
of problems that do actually have to be
solved hands on with I take a lightning
network being the canonical example of
that yeah then what happens though as
you explore the space of possibility
that opens up within the domain of the
Bitcoin approach what you see at the
edge of that space is a path that is
computation turned completion and for
those remember the history there was
actually that what ended up happening at
different alt coins who began trying to
explore the space that possibility that
lipid is the design capacity of the
Bitcoin style blockchain and they ran up
against the edge of Turing completeness
which was well we kind of need to step
back and do a comprehensive redesign
we need to actually re-enter the space
of pure architecture and think about the
problem in its purest sense you'll
really move into again into a design
space and and think about the whole
thing all at once think about all the
different parameters all the different
elements of how they feedback on each
other don't try to run an iterative
process launch a new project on a
completely new basis or an importantly
new basis a theorem and go so you
couldn't get to it aetherium is a merely
progressing organically from Bitcoin you
actually had to take Bitcoin as a as a
hint
stepping back rethink the whole thing
launch a new design approach and bam so
you kind of have these trade-offs
between McMichael high design and
organic development mm-hmm
and the Dow is of that same order
obvious the beginning part of this video
talked about fundamental theoretical
problem but it's many many different
things of driving that that you cannot
get to the Dow through organic
development on top of the etherium
platform you could do some interesting
things you can build ways of doing
governance you can build ways of having
collaborative economies but the the
problem space is actually more
fundamental than that and so it's
necessary to step back radically expand
the scope of considerations think about
the entire systems design as a whole
really do design in the way the design
is supposed to be done and then once
you've actually really gotten down to
you make all conceptual clarity what are
the really important pieces what are the
fundamental elements that must be in
place in the right way and how they
feedback and relate to each other then
you instantiate it as a technical
architecture as a protocol and then once
you've done that you get you move back
into the space of organic development
mm-hm and then you're then you're
running right if you've got it right
he's entered into a new space which
is equivalent to these kind of major
tones Bitcoin etherium so I think that's
the frame there's a kind of approach and
a style and a capacity for design
thinking and four fundamental thinking
and I think thinking in a fundamental
fashion that is I believe necessary to
truly grasp the question of the Dow and
it is only when that has been done
appropriately and then instantiated that
we have moved into this new era and
that's I think that's kind of the way to
understand it the if you try if you want
to understand what's going on in the Dow
space this conceptual distinction
between high design and organic
development I think is helpful to make
sense of it yeah if you draw the analogy
to the organic development in the
direction of turing completeness in
bitcoin and high design in the
innovation of its cerium I think is the
analogy if that makes sense to you then
I think you're in a good in good shape
to navigate this space if it doesn't
make sense to you then hopefully you
have other ways of making sense if you
want to jump into this space because
it's not at all trivial yeah it sounds
like in your view the rise of
decentralized collaboration represents
the third major movement in the
evolution of blockchain yeah I think
that's exactly the right way of thinking
about it you can think about these as
major and minor tones or major and minor
movements and this is a major movement
and it would be the third major movement
and I have to admit that from an
aesthetic perspective I can't prove this
no what I even try but intuitively this
may in fact be the reason now if you
think about the the magnitude of
consequence you have what I described is
what happens when you really figure out
how to build an anti rivals economic
architecture
if we say 400 years in the future we
look back at this story if it turns out
that we had cracked the code on anti
robberies then that will have been why
we did all of this in the first place
mm-hmm and requires a completely
bottom-up approach integrated with
high-level design yes and in fact what I
would say is that the if you think about
the essence of what design means really
design means simultaneously something
that is fully bottoms up and fully
talked out yeah you have to actually be
able to grasp both simultaneously and
understand the synergistic consequences
of relating them appropriately and
sounds like for you one of the geniuses
of Dow stack is the attention to and
facility in both bottom-up and top-down
approaches to architecture and design
yes the kinds of people who have been
gathered around it have that capability
and also have that consciousness meaning
that they are not just doing it but
they're aware of the fact that they're
doing it and in many ways why mmhmm yeah
although they are continuing to struggle
to figure out how to articulate it which
is not not surprising it's hard it's new
territory yeah yeah anything else you
want to mention while we're talking
about the contribution that Dow stock
might be able to make within the greater
Dowie ecosystem I could kind of hold out
specific pieces so within the concept of
design there is this well actually we
just came in so we'll zoom into a lower
level so how do we instantiate this
notion of top-down and bottom-up
simultaneously well with this with you
think about then is constructing an
architecture that is set up in such a
way that it is simultaneously modular
and fundamentally open meaning that it
can go to where it needs to go but also
is
creates boundary conditions that make
and focus people's energy and attention
so that it's not a random search right
of the whole space so this is many
people just call this good architecture
but like that's that's a good
architecture it's genius
creating something which has the
capacity to be very fluid and open
modular in many ways easy to build and
construct on but at the same time is how
has a set of intrinsic boundary
conditions and initial conditions such
that the right kinds of bottoms-up
choices are probabilistically likely to
show up and to be sensed in such a way
that they reinforce each other mm-hmm is
an act of genius and interesting I'm not
sure if this is gonna be clarifying to
anybody but it's actually the kind of
thing that happened in Minecraft when
notch built minecraft and I think the
gigantic success of Minecraft I think is
not confusing he was able to build
something which was a sandbox yeah it
was this inbox that also had the right
kind of elements to cause people to
actually play yeah in the sandbox in a
way that was both fun and generative
yeah I was just gonna make a sandbox
analogy myself
it's like dow stock is providing not so
much a fixed offering in decentralized
governance or a fixed set of software
tools even but rather a kind of sandbox
for ongoing experimentation in
decentralized governance and as such
provides the sandbox infrastructure like
the sand as well as maybe a set of
initial toys and tools to play with the
initial it's it's the combination tech
if all I get so the the the Sahara
Desert is not a sandbox right it's it's
a it's a it's a disaster it's the
potential is to open you can't do
anything with it
mm-hmm sandbox is something that has the
ability to be extremely open and fluid
but
the same time has the right kinds of
constraints hints and elements that
actual structure will emerge on it yep
which is I mean the if anybody spends
time speaking to Matan and Adam by the
way both of whom I know reasonably well
I don't know a whole lot of the other
folks as well so if you speak to any of
them yeah it doesn't take but a few
seconds if you're paying attention to
recognize that you're dealing with a
kind of mind that is not well normal and
I mean that in the mathematical sense
and also with a psychological sense
that's the kind of mind that one would
hope is what you'd put on this kind of a
project yeah yeah great I feel like this
could be a good place to wrap is there
anything else you'd like to add no I
feel like that was actually I thought it
was pretty good yeah yeah I think we
covered some great territory so Jordan
thanks a lot for your time it was great
talking with you like to see but all
right okay